<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ezekiel the prophet explained as follows</title>
            <author>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1988A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897294</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897294</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2481:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ezekiel the prophet explained as follows</title>
                  <author>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Signed and dated at end: April 2. 1647. Eleanor.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2481 bound and filmed preceding Wing D1988.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezekiel I --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:137019:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137019:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>EZEKIEL</hi> THE PROPHET Explained as follows.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <add>His writ serued of Rebellion, Lamentation Mourning and Woe</add>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O many having attempted the ſtraits or paſſages of this Labyrinth, and loſt their labor who went about it, could not but drop a word, have thought it not amiſſe or unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as wiſe as they are that miſſed their mark, a taſte or touch to give them, of the tree of Life, otherwiſe cald the myſtery of Times and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, reſerved for the laſt time, this Sacramental little Rowl, with ſuch a ſolemn proteſtation bound touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:137019:2"/>times being no longer, which precious Manna, the Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt both taſted of, not longed for a little (<hi>Acts</hi> 1)</p>
            <p>But haſtning on <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. now in the Thirtieth year, &amp;c. <hi>And I looked, and behold a Whirl-wind came out of the North, a great cloud, &amp;c.</hi> where thoſe winged living creatures four, &amp;c. repreſented by the Tabernacle; alſo the Lamp, &amp;c. as it were thoſe Curtains, every one of one mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure joyned one to another with ſo many loops or eyes, and rings above ſo high, beſides their running ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, like thoſe ſwift creatures who went on their ſides when they ran, their diſplayed wings ſending forth ſuch a noiſe, of a ſpherical work, &amp;c.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137019:2"/>And ſo much for theſe Curtains of his Pavilion, typifying the four Evangeliſts agreeing in one, ſaid to kiſſe or touch, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>VVhereof <hi>Apocalyps</hi> the Fourth thus, of the aforeſaid four Beaſts, and the Lightning proceeding out of the Throne, ſhews firſt of the Lamp; <hi>And there were Seven Lamps of fire, which are the Seven Spirits of God, &amp;c.</hi> Cap. 5. <hi>The Seven Spirits and Seven Eyes ſent forth into all the Earth,</hi> as their Characters ☉ <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> read through the world.</p>
            <p>So to ſhew the truth of it, even the full Moon deſcribed its paleneſs in the Saphir-like Firmament, and no other likened to the Amber, and Fire its brightneſſe, when this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137019:3"/>or gift of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Giving withal to underſtand, received or rejecting it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding how Propheſie ceaſed not, nor the Spirit (as the world would have it) totally is quenched; But the VVrit or Label of this little ſealed Rowl being firſt ſerved on them, cald a houſe of Rebellion, or a rebellious houſe ſo often; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to be ſerved again, reſerved even for our days, as if any be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obſerve, directed to our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth Century, by the ſlain Lamb, Redemptions figure, <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. having ſeven Horns, and as many EYES; alſo witneſſe the grand Iury, thoſe Twenty four Crowned Elders, ſo many times mentioned,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137019:3"/>and as ſhewing ſince the Conqueſt Four and twenty Crowned, ſo Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred years ago thereabout.</p>
            <p>And thus going on when this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Writ</hi> to be ſerved, how it came to paſſe; how diſtaſteful to them, <hi>hony in the mouth, bitter in the belly;</hi> compared to a womans travel, or as fares with Officers earning a Fee venture their lives upon Arreſts, even the ſum of this Viſion reſtleſſe Priſons deſcription, clouded under the glory of the Tabernacle, ſets forth a Chamber-Bedſted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances, the Gatehouſe priſon, in the year of Redemption, 1634. <hi>September</hi> 24. full Moon the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Lamp, priſoners fire and candle, who from the Angel ſent thither the Holy Ghoſt, that by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137019:4"/>ſpace of an hour, the Bed his throne reſted thereon, from his mouth for a farewel received a ſalute; and for another farewel, that had on his right hand an Amber glove, left ſuch an odoriferous ſcent when he was gone, all oyled with Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece, the ſpirit thereof proceeding from the Leather, ſo far beyond expreſsion, as it were inviſible food, like when as ſaid, <hi>Cauſe thy b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly to eat, and fill thy bowels,</hi> the hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent to him with the Rowl or Book ſpread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a Holy, holy, holy day, by whom obſerved ever ſince.</p>
            <p>And for Lamentations, Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and VVoe, ſuch cryed up and down: So much for this time cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto, <hi>O Wheel, cap.</hi> 10. beſides
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137019:4"/>proclaims winged Times reign in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes years, containing the four Seaſons, Moneths, VVeeks, Days and Hours, not returning reſtleſſe time, with the Clock wheel its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, likewiſe Rings out the Abbey Bells, thoſe mounted wheels, <hi>Verſe</hi> 18. <hi>Verſe</hi> 19. like theſe living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures likened to burniſhed Braſſe, with their aſcending and deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and for the dreadful Rings ſo much, &amp;c. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 18. that were ſo high, their ſound or noiſe like great waters, the Voice of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty coming from Heaven, as it were: And ſo farther for that ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious round VVindow, the glaſſe its curious work compared to the <hi>Beril</hi> of a Sea-green colour, as the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtaline Heaven all with one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137019:5"/>voice proclaim the dreadful Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day reveald at hand, to a City moſt rebellious.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under the hands of thoſe <hi>Cherubs,</hi> under their wings that had hands, with that hand ſent, &amp;c. ſeals and ſignifies it, rings out Times farewel: And for the word of the Lord expreſly ſo much. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. <hi>Write the things which thou haſt ſeen, and the things which are, and the things which ſhall be hereafter.</hi> 
                  <date>April 2. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Eleanor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
